# André Carvalho

Website My Portfolio - https://afcarvalho1991.github.io

**Email** afccarvalho.1991@gmail.com

Mobile Phone +351 91 845 44 57 Nationality Portuguese

#### Currently

#### 2019 Data Scientist and Researcher - Instituto Soldadura e Qualidade

- Application and research of deep neural networks solutions, to identify olive tree plagues using European Space Agency (ESA) hyperspectral satellite imagery;

Responsible for Planing and dev. of the System architecture (front-end and backend); Development of deep learning models; Front-end development.

Technologies and frameworks: TensorFlow, keras, keras-tuner, OpenCV, rasterio, Matplotlib, Multiprocessing, Flask, Angular, TypeScript, HTML, CSS, Git.

- Application and research of deep neural networks solutions, to improve Deep Sea Mining of mineral resources, using European Space Agency (ESA) hyperspectral satellite imagery;

Responsible for System Architecture (front-end and back-end) planing and development; Research and application of deep learning models;

Design and Dev. of RESTful front-end and back-end communication API;

Communication with clients, to share progresses ideas and deciding the following steps.

Technologies and frameworks: TensorFlow, keras, keras-tuner, OpenCV, rasterio, Matplotlib, Multiprocessing, Flask, Angular, TypeScript, HTML, CSS, Git;

- Predictive maintenance to identify machinery malfunctions at an industrial scale.

Dev. of database architecture i.e. relational model;

Dev. of web-based management platform (deploy by me via EC2 - AWS);

Dev. of automatic report system;

Dev. of machine learning models to predict possible malfunctions.

Communication with clients in order to decided the following development stages;

Technologies and frameworks: Scikit-learn, Matplotlib, Flask, created REST-API, PostgreSQL, Angular, TypeScript, OpenMaint, HTML, CSS, Latex, Git;

- Optimization of water supply systems distribution network using machine-learning models.

Software engineer role:

- Restructure and refactor existing code to a OOP approach to support future developments;
- Prepare and implement code to be used in high-performance computing infrastructures;
- Use AWS cloud computing services to speedup a custom optimization algorithm intended to improve pump scheduling.

Technologies and frameworks: keras, numpy, sklearn, multiprocessing, Matplotlib, AWS, Flask, created REST-API, PostgreSQL, Angular, TypeScript, OpenMaint, HTML, CSS, Latex, Git;

### **Past Experience**

2017-2018 Lab Professor - Foundations of Programming
 1 Semester Instituto Superior Técnico, Lisbon, Portugal

Lectures on topics such as Python3, Object-oriented programming, Lists, HashTables, Map-Reduce

Lab Professor - Introduction to Algorithms and Data Structures

2 Semester In:

2016-2017

Instituto Superior Técnico, Lisbon, Portugal

Lectures on topics: C language, iterative and recursive algorithms, Sorting algorithms: direct sort, selection sort, bubble sort, quick sort, merge sort. Data types: stacks, queues, priority queues and heaps. Searching in trees. Dynamic data structures. Binary trees. Balanced binary trees. Hash tables. Collision resolution by chaining and open addressing. Double hashing.

### Skills e Experience

- Machine-learning, Computer Vision, Deep Learning
- Python, C, Typescript, Java, Matlab, Bash (among others)
- Angular, Flask(+waitress), Node.JS, JS, HTML, CSS
- ElasticSearch, MongoDB, SQL, S3
- Docker, Kubernetes, AWS, HPC, Hadoop, Spark
- Git, Unit Testing, Jira, Teams, Slack, Discord, Agile

#### Education

2015-2019 PhD Information Systems and Computer Engineering - Instituto Superior Técnico

Passed with distinction

Focused on improving recommendation systems computational efficiency by leveraging Fuzzy Fingerprints.

2012-2014 MSc Telecommunications and Informatics Engineering - Instituto Superior Técnico

Thesis grade 17

Final grade 16

Development of a recommendation system that identifies relevant keywords and maps them for each user.

**2009-2012** BSc Computer Networks and Multimedia Engineering - Inst. Superior de Engenharia de Lisboa

Third Year Project grade 18

Final grade 15

Car track stopwatch using computer vision and machine learning models to identify different cars that pass by.

## **Publications**

■ Tag-Based User Fuzzy Fingerprints for Recommender Systems [url]
May, 2018

• Fuzzy fingerprints for item-based collaborative filtering [url]

Nominated for Best Student Paper Award September, 2017

Combining ratings and item descriptions in recommendation systems using fuzzy fingerprints [url]
 July, 2017

# **Personal interests**

- Tennis
- Financial markets
- Travelling
- Photography